Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania, 1969-1975; VII.
  - Public Statements, 3.
    - 1972 (Box 36, Folder 4)
      - Remarks to the Tri-State Environmental Symposium regarding the role of United States Attorneys, January 12, 1972; 2.
      - Thornburgh defended wiretapping activities carried on by the federal government in Western Pennsylvania, January 13, 1972; 3.
      - Federal efforts to deal decisively with the problem of drug abuse are accelerating on all fronts, January 31, 1972; 4.
      - Federal revenue-sharing in the criminal justice area is already underway, February 3, 1972; 5.
      - Disorganized police cannot deal effectively with organized crime, February 4, 1972; 6.
      - Our criminal justice system cannot work without the free flow of testimony in open court, February 14, 1972; 7.
      - Protection payoffs by racketeers to law enforcement deprive the community of the protection it pays for through its tax dollars, February 17, 1972; 8.
      - Community demands upon our police are not matched by community concern for their well-being, February 19, 1972; 9.
      - Organized crime is not just something you read about, it is alive and well in Western Pennsylvania, March 6, 1972; 10.
      - Efforts to deal with the problem of narcotics and dangerous drugs must be directed toward both the areas of supply and demand, March 14, 1972; 11.
      - Congress has directed federal law enforcement agencies to root out the 'politico racket complex' that controls local government in some Western Pennsylvania cities, March 28, 1972; 12.
      - Organized crime and street crime go hand in hand in Allegheny County, April 15, 1972; 13.
      - Thornburgh gave the keynote address, "The Individual's Rights in America," to kick off Law Week at Indiana University, May 1, 1972; 14.
      - Efforts to sweep official corruption under the rug can only serve the interests of the corrupters, May 4, 1972; 15.
      - Hard work by the FBI, in cooperation with local police\, has resulted in a solution rate in area bank robbery cases of around 80 percent, May 11, 1972; 16.
      - Allegheny County's 116 separate police forces could be reduced by combination and merger and our citizenry would reap the benefits., May 17, 1972; 17.
      - We must begin to face up to hard questions about the social malignancy of drug abuse, May 18, 1972; 18.
      - Handgun laws should provide that no one can purchase, own or possess a handgun unless they show a good reason or a real need to do so, May 20, 1972; 19.
      - Today's policeman needs his own lawyer if he is to maximize his crime-fighting capacity, May 23, 1972; 20.
      - This week's Supreme Court decision upholding the witness immunity provisions of the Federal Organized Crime Control Act validates an important weapon in our battle against the mob, May 24, 1972; 21.
      - The searchlight of a special federal grand jury will begin focusing on local traffickers in narcotics and dangerous drugs, May 26, 1972; 22.
      - Juveniles account for more than one-half of the arrests for serious crimes in Allegheny County, June 6, 1972; 23.
      - The first federal grand jury ever specially empanelled to look into organized crime and racketeering in Western Pennsylvania, will complete its service next month, June 23, 1972; 24.
      - The tide is finally beginning to turn in the battle against organized crime, July 25, 1972; 25.
      - Allegheny County's failure to activate a county-wide anti-narcotics force is inexcusable, August 8, 1972
      - The federal government aims to put the organized crime syndicates out of business in Western Pennsylvania, September 11, 1972; 26.
      - The federal government is fully geared up to combat the influence of the racket syndicates, September 14, 1972; 27.
      - Congress has directed federal law enforcement agencies to root out the 'politico racket complex' that controls local government, and we are beginning to show results, October 19, 1972; 28.
      - Some way must be found to demonstrate the dollars and cents imperative of correctional reform, October 23, 1972; 29.
      - Can government inaction frustrate citizen efforts to clean up the environment?, October 26, 1972; 30.
      - There is a real connection between street crimes of violence and the operations of organized crime in this nation, November 3, 1972; 31.
      - Organized crime had a fifty-year head start on effective law enforcement, but we are beginning to close the gap, November 9, 1972; 32.
      - We must begin to face up to hard questions about the social malignancy of drug abuse, November 12, 1972; 33.
      - The average Western Pennsylvania businessman may well be supporting organized crime without knowing it, November 16, 1972; 34.
      - Our system of criminal justice is designed to secure maximum protection to the total community and to each individual citizen, November 22, 1972; 35.
    - 1973 (Box 36, Folder 5)
      - 1973 will be a year of continued pressure on organized crime and racketeering in Western Pennsylvania, January 2, 1973; 1.
      - Illegal wiretapping constitutes a major threat to the privacy and civil liberties of all our citizens, January 9, 1973; 2.
      - There is a real connection between street crimes of violence and the operations of organized crime in this nation, January 14, 1973; 3.
      - Any invasion of the criminal justice system by partisan politics should be of great concern, January 18, 1973; 4.
      - Federal investigations have revealed the specific patterns utilized by the 'politico-racket complex' to neutralize Pennsylvania's anti-gambling laws, February 14, 1973; 5.
      - Outmoded procedures in our courts constitute a major bottleneck in today's criminal justice system, February 22, 1973; 6.
      - We are accustomed to hearing charges of 'politics' in connection with the prosecution of criminal cases by the federal government, February 27, 1973; 7.
      - Vigorous enforcement efforts are beginning to shrink the profitable heroin racket in Western Pennsylvania, February 28, 1973; 8.
      - Aggressive investigative reporting by the news media is particularly important in the fields of organized crime\, racketeering and official corruption, March 1, 1973; 9.
      - Our system of criminal justice is designed to secure maximum protection to the total community and to each individual citizen, March 16, 1973; 10.
      - Police officers should get as good legal advice in carrying out their duties as the public provides for criminal defendants, March 29, 1973; 11.
      - Prosecution of 'crime in the suites' must command an equal priority with violent offenses in law enforcement efforts, April 24, 1973; 12.
      - Legislation setting minimum standards for becoming a policeman in Pennsylvania is long overdue, April 26, 1973; 13.
      - Reform of our police, courts and correctional systems must be systematically undertaken, May 2, 1973; 14.
      - Thornburgh outlined ten priority action areas to improve Allegheny County's criminal justice system, June 4, 1973; 15.
      - A supplemental pension fund for retired state troopers received contributions from a firm fronting for the mob, June 9, 1973; 16.
      - The abiding lesson of Watergate is clear. Our system continues to work, June 16, 1973; 17.
      - Americans are learning that partisan politics can be a serious polluter of effective law enforcement, August 15, 1973; 18.
      - The overreach of our criminal laws is proving to be a major hindrance to effective law enforcement, September 28, 1973; 19.
      - Businessmen should demand release of the 'shopper's guide to the rackets' prepared by the Pennsylvania Crime Commission, October 17, 1973; 20.
      - Policemen have the biggest stake in seeking to remove the influence of the 'politico-racket complex' from law enforcement in Western Pennsylvania, November 9, 1973; 21.
      - Some of the crimes most destructive to the fabric of our society are carried out by those in business suits, November 11, 1973; 22.
      - Organized crime had a fifty-year head start on effective law enforcement, but we are beginning to close the gap, November 15, 1973; 23.
      - Our view of wrong doing in high places is sometimes distorted by our vantage point. Only a vigilant public and aggressive law enforcement can prevent its reach into any community, November 28, 1973; 24.
      - We must recognize the Watergate phenomenon as a basic challenge to our political process, December 11, 1973; 25.
      - The federal government plays a vital, but limited, role in law enforcement in Western Pennsylvania, December 12, 1973; 26.
    - 1974 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - We are beginning to turn the corner in the battle against organized crime, January 8, 1974; 1.
      - Show and tell must become the rule for political candidates and office holders with respect to their sources of income and campaign contributions, January 15, 1974; 2.
      - Why is the 'shopper's guide to the rackets' prepared, but never published, by the Pennsylvania Crime Commission?, January 21, 1974; 3.
      - Flushing out those on the take will constitute a high priority for federal law enforcement efforts in 1974, January 22, 1974; 4.
      - We are only now beginning to face up to hard questions about the social malignancy of drug abuse, January 30, 1974; 5.
      - The federal government plays a vital, but limited, role in law enforcement in Western Pennsylvania, February 15, 1974; 6.
      - The overreach of our criminal laws is proving to be a major hindrance to effective law enforcement, February 16, 1974; 7.
      - Our criminal justice system puts a high premium on protecting the rights of the individual, and that is as it should be, March 10, 1974; 8.
      - Support your local police' must become more than just a bumper-sticker slogan if we are to have safer communities in our nation, March 15, 1974; 9.
      - State and local police will assume a much expanded role in fighting street level drug traffic under new federal guidelines, April 5, 1974; 10.
      - Recent pronouncements by public officials would seem to encourage, rather than deter, the spread of the stain of public corruption throughout Pennsylvania, April 9, 1974; 11.
      - Current crime statistics pinpoint Allegheny County's suburbs as the site of the real crime problems in our community, April 29, 1974; 12.
      - Federal investigations have revealed the specific patterns utilized by the 'politico-racket complex' to neutralize Pennsylvania's anti-gambling laws, April 30, 1974; 13.
      - Western Pennsylvania businessmen may well be supporting organized crime and racketeering without knowing it, May 2, 1974; 14.
      - Thornburgh called for a three-point effort to reduce the incidence of public corruption, May 11, 1974; 15.
      - Thornburgh spoke on "You and Organized Crime" at the annual dinner meeting of the Beaver-Lawrence County Savings and Loan League, May 23, 1974; 15.
      - The number one challenge to federal law enforcement efforts in Western Pennsylvania are those criminal offenses which affect the integrity of the government, May 25, 1974; 16.
      - Those who preach a message of violence, bombing, and terrorism have no standing in American society. They must be excised form the legitimate community, June 15, 1974; 17.
      - A ten-year pattern of widespread and systematic corruption among Pittsburgh area law enforcement units responsible for fighting organized crime has been revealed by federal prosecutors, July 1, 1974; 18.
      - Show and tell must become the rule for political candidates and office holders with respect to their sources of income and campaign contributions, July 5, 1974; 19.
      - We are beginning to turn the corner in the battle against organized crime and racketeering in Western Pennsylvania, September 4, 1974; 20.
      - The only way to cut down on the number of handguns in the wrong hands is to cut down on the number of handguns, September 9, 1974; 21.
      - Sentencing practices have gone haywire in our criminal courts, September 10, 1974; 22.
      - State run lotteries, legal race track betting and illegal bingo encourage organized crime's monopoly in numbers and sports betting, September 19, 1974; 23.
      - The new legal weaponry of the 1970s has sparked federal government's successful drive against organized crime, September 24, 1974; 24.
      - The cry of 'politics' seems to have become the death rattle of crooked public officials facing criminal indictment, October 10, 1974; 25.
      - Organized crime gets by with more than a little help from its friends. The mob receives substantial aid from some unlikely sources, November 6, 1974; 26.
      - A pattern of widespread corruption among Pittsburgh area law enforcement units responsible for fighting organized crime, has been revealed by federal prosecutions, November 8, 1974; 27.
      - Federal efforts to crack down on the rackets' monopoly of illegal gambling is not some moral crusade, November 14, 1974; 28.
      - The conviction of Senator Frank Mazzei on federal extortion charges raised more questions than it answered, December 4, 1974; 29.
      - Undue solicitude for those who betray the public trust only makes the task of rooting out political parasites more difficult, December 12, 1974; 30.
      - The overreach of our criminal laws is proving to be a major hindrance to effective law enforcement, December 15, 1974; 32.
    - 1975 (Box 36, Folder 7)
      - Partisan politics has no place in the administration of justice, January 8, 1975; 1.
      - Rip-offs by crooks in business suits or high governmental positions are costing American citizens millions of dollars in hidden costs, January 20, 1975; 2.
      - Only aggressive prosecution can remove the 'For Sale' sign from public office, January 22, 1975; 3.
      - Investigation of official corruption is a must if our political and governmental institutions are to survive and prosper, January 31, 1975; 4.
      - When kickbacks are extorted on government leases, it is the taxpayer who picks up the tab, February 12, 1975; 5.
      - Can we control and contain organized crime? It is a simple matter of supply and demand, February 15, 1975; 6.
      - Federal prosecutors have focused successfully on state and local corruption because most state and local agencies are unable to do the job, February 21, 1975; 7.
      - Organized crime's 'politico-racket complex' had a fifty year head start on effective law enforcement, but we are beginning to close the gap, March 5, 1975; 8.
      - Disclosures of public corruption are more than just a cause for despair, March 15, 1975; 9.
      - An epidemic of corruption in high public office can only be stifled by strong doses of effective law enforcement, March 29, 1975; 10.
      - Cash and carry politics is at the bottom of most of the corrupt schemes uncovered by recent federal prosecutions, April 24, 1975; 11.
      - Today's governmental lawlessness may pose more of a threat to our system of justice than the most hardened gunman, May 1, 1975; 12.
      - Proposed changes in the federal Rules of Criminal Procedure can have a disastrous effect on the prosecution of criminal cases, June 20, 1975; 13.
  - Events, 4.
    Folders in this subseries are arranged chronologically by month. Each folder contains materials related to events that Thornburgh attended while he served as U.S. Attorney. Events include: speaking engagements, dinners, ceremonies, conferences, and symposia. Event materials include invitations, correspondence, memoranda, issue background, annotated notes, and ephemera.
    - 1969 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - January, 1970 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - February, 1970 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - March, 1970 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - April, 1970 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - May, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - June, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - July, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - August, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - September, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - October, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - November, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - December, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - January, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - February, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - March, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - April, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - May, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - June, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - July, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - August, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - September, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - October, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - November, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 19)
    - December, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 20)
    - January, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 21)
    - February, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 22)
    - March, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 23)
    - April, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 24)
    - May, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 25)
    - June, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 26)
    - July, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 27)
    - August, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 28)
    - September, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 29)
    - October, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 30)
    - November, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 31)
    - January, 1973 (Box 37, Folder 32)
    - February, 1973 (Box 37, Folder 33)
    - March, 1973 (Box 37, Folder 34)
    - April, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - May, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - June, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - July, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - August, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - September, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - October, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - November, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - December, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - January, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - February, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - March, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - April, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - May, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - June, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - July, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - August, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 17)
    - September, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 18)
    - October, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 19)
    - November, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 20)
    - December, 1974 (Box 38, Folder 21)
    - January, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 22)
    - February, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 23)
    - March, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 24)
    - April, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 25)
    - May, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 26)
    - June, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 5.
    The correspondence files consist of the four groupings originally maintained by the U.S. Attorney's office. First, congratulatory correspondence, arranged chronologically. Secondly, also in chronological order by month, is correspondence to and from Thornburgh. Third, there is alphabetically arranged correspondence, for example: A-D, June 1969-June 1975. Both the chronological and alphabetical files contain correspondence to and from Thornburgh and may have some overlap. Fourth, there is correspondence separated by either to or from Thornburgh.
    - Congratulatory Correspondence
      - May 6, 1969-June 5, 1969 (Box 38, Folder 28)
      - June 6, 1969-August 14, 1969 (Box 38, Folder 29)
    - Chronological Correspondence
      - June 5, 1969-October 3, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - October 6, 1969-December 31, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - January 2,1970 -March 31, 1970 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - April 1, 1970-June 30, 1970 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - July 1, 1970-October 30, 1970 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      - November 2, 1970-December 30, 1970 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      - January 4, 1971-March 31, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 7)
      - April 1, 1971-July 30, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 8)
      - August 2, 1971-October 29, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 9)
      - November 1, 1971-December 29, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 10)
      - January 3, 1972-March 31, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 11)
      - April 3, 1972-July 31, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 12)
      - August 1, 1972-December 31, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 13)
      - January 2, 1973-April 30, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 14)
      - May 1, 1973-September 28, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 15)
      - October 1, 1973-December 26, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 16)
      - January 3, 1974-April 30, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 17)
      - May 1, 1974-August 30, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 18)
      - September 3, 1974-December 31, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 19)
      - January 1, 1975-March 28, 1975 (Box 39, Folder 20)
      - April 1, 1975-July 3, 1975 (Box 39, Folder 21)
    - Alphabetical Correspondence
      - A-D, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 1)
      - E-H, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 2)
      - I-L, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - M-P, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 4)
      - Q-S, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 5)
      - T-V, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 6)
      - W-Z, June, 1969-June, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence To and From Thornburgh
      - Correspondence to and from Thornburgh, June 11, 1969-December 30, 1970 (Box 40, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence to and from Thornburgh, January 5, 1971-December 23, 1971 (Box 40, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence to and from Thornburgh, January 3, 1972-December 29, 1972 (Box 40, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence to and from Thornburgh, January, 1973-July, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence from Thornburgh, 1970-1975 (Box 40, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence to Thornburgh, 1971-1977 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - United States Attorney of Western Pennsylvania's Files, 6.
    These files contain information kept close at hand by Thornburgh for his personal reference. Here, for example, is the transcript of his swearing in ceremony, accomplishments of his time as USA, annotated issue materials, Thornburgh articles written and published, staff notes and committee reports of significance, including some related to the strike forces. These files serve as an interesting personal overview of Thornburgh's years as U.S. Attorney.
    - Thornburgh Biographies, 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Thornburgh, U.S. Attorney, miscellaneous, 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Appointment and reappointment, U.S. Attorney, 1969, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Transcription of "Swearing In Ceremony of Richard L. Thornburgh as United States Attorney for the Western District of Pennsylvania", June 6, 1969 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Unpublished Article by Thornburgh regarding narcotics and judicial reform, undated (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - "Accomplishments of the Office of Richard L. Thornburgh, U.S. Attorney for Western Pennsylvania", 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - U.S. Attorney Office Staff Notes, 1970-1975 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Thornburgh's Notes From U.S. Attorneys Conferences, 1969-1973 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Petition for home rule in Pittsburgh, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - "Support Your Local Police: The Case for Strict Handgun Controls," by Richard Thornburgh, Juris, Vol. VI, No. 1 (includes background material and correspondence), 1972 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - "Changing Priorities in the United States Attorney's Office," by Richard Thornburgh, Juris, Vol. Viii No. 2 (includes background material), December 1974 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Notes on Criminal Justice, 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Reports on the Pennsylvania Crime Commission, 1969-1974 (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Pennsylvania Crime Commission: Legislation and Hearings, 1972-1973 (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence regarding the infiltration of legitimate business by Organized Crime, 1972-1974 (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - 1899 Refuse Act Prosecution, 1971-1972 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Third Regional Symposium on Careers in Criminal Justice, Indiana University of Pennsylvania, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Reference Materials on Supreme Court Decisions, 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 18)
    - Testimony regarding proposed amendments to Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, September 17, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 19)